<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions on Mr. Hill's book entituled, A vindication of the primitive fathers, against the imputations of Gilbert, Lord Bishop of Sarum in a letter to a person of quality.</title>
            <author>Allix, Pierre, 1641-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23822</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22827</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12490732</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12490732</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62374</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23822)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62374)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 302:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions on Mr. Hill's book entituled, A vindication of the primitive fathers, against the imputations of Gilbert, Lord Bishop of Sarum in a letter to a person of quality.</title>
                  <author>Allix, Pierre, 1641-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 65, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ri. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by P. Allix. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.); DNB.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [1]-[3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hill, Samuel, 1648-1716. --  Vindication of the primitive fathers against the imputations of Gilbert Lord Bishop of Sarum.</term>
               <term>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:62374:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANIMADVERSIONS ON Mr. <hi>HILL</hi>'s BOOK, ENTITULED, <hi>A Vindication of the Primitive Fathers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62374:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62374:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANIMADVERSIONS ON Mr.</hi> HILL<hi>'s BOOK, ENTITULED,</hi> A Vindication of the Primitive Fathers, againſt the Imputations of <hi>GILBERT,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Letter to a Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>LONDON: <hi>Printed for <hi>Ri. Chiſwell,</hi> at the</hi> Roſe <hi>and</hi> Crown <hi>in St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Church-Yard. 1695.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62374:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62374:3"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS ON Mr. <hi>HILL</hi>'s BOOK, ENTITULED, <hi>A Vindication of the Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N obedience to your Commands, I here ſend you my Thoughts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s <hi>Book;</hi> the whole of which conſiſts of Four Heads. The <hi>Firſt</hi> contains a Cenſure of what the Biſhop compendiouſly ſuppoſes concerning the Doctrine of the Trinity. The <hi>Second</hi> Criticiſes upon what he ſays about the Myſtery of the Incarnation. The <hi>Third</hi> is a Vindication of the Fathers, whom he thinks the Biſhop has treated very ill, as to the Explication they have given of theſe Two Myſteries. The <hi>Fourth</hi> and laſt is an Explanation of the Myſtery of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62374:4"/> the Trinity, which he advances as much more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Syſtem of Scripture, and of the Ancients, than the Biſhop's.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> picks a Quarrel with the Biſhop, becauſe in ſpeaking of the Perſuaſions of <hi>Socinians, Arians,</hi> and <hi>Orthodox,</hi> concerning the Nature of Chriſt, he calls them three different <hi>Opinions.</hi> He would not have had the Biſhop uſe the word <hi>Opinion,</hi> in ſpeaking of that which we look upon as founded on Divine Revelation, and receive as the Object of our Faith. This doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs is a moſt heinous Crime, which deſerved all Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Exaggerations, tho <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> has uſed the ſame word, <hi>Orat.</hi> 35. Certainly, when an Author undertakes to conſider the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Tenets touching the Nature of Jeſus Chriſt, namely, that of <hi>Artemas,</hi> that of <hi>Arius,</hi> and that of the <hi>Church;</hi> he may, I think, without a Crime, call them three <hi>Opinions;</hi> eſpecially, as the Biſhop has done, before he had proved any thing by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation. Every body knows that ſtrong Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are not to be uſed in the ſtating of a queſtion, but only after the matter has been well proved. So that a Criticiſm of this Nature, gives us no great Character of the Author.</p>
            <p>With as much ſincerity does Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring under ſuſpicion the Biſhop's Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, becauſe he does not diſtinctly ſay, whether the <hi>Socinian</hi> or <hi>Arian</hi> Opinions, have been within or without the Church. <q>For, ſays he, <hi>page</hi> 2. if the Biſhop ſuppoſes that theſe Opinions have been within the Church: Then indeed here is an Inſinuation laid for the Communion with <hi>Socinians,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62374:4"/> which is a bleſſed comprehenſion.</q> This he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats or inſinuates again ſomewhere elſe. If a <hi>Pagan</hi> had made this Reflection againſt a Biſhop, he might have been charged with want of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. But what can we ſay, when theſe words come from the Mouth of a Prieſt, againſt a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> And what means Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> when he finds fault with the Notion of Faith given by the Biſhop; to wit, that we believe Points of Doctrine, becauſe we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that they are revealed in Scripture? Does it follow from thence, as Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſuppoſes, p. 6. <hi>That Faith reſolves it ſelf into each private Man's Opinion?</hi> Which indeed has occaſioned all the Hereſies and Diviſions that have been in the Church.</p>
            <p>This Cenſure has ſomewhat ſo ſingular in it, that it well deſerves to be taken notice of; and I promiſe you to remember it, and to ſhew you that the Author eſpouſes a Principle as dangerous as any in Point of Religion. But I muſt not do this at preſent, for it would lead us out of our way, and bring us off from the Article of the Trinity, which we have now chiefly in view.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> pretends that the Biſhop does not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain himſelf clearly upon this Myſtery. Theſe are his ſurmiſes. The Biſhop has not diſtinctly ſet down that there are Three Perſons; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Biſhop, who does not expreſs himſelf by the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> which is received in this matter, gives a right to any one to ſay, that he denies the Trinity; whereas this at moſt were but <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bellia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm.</hi> Upon this unjuſt foundation he takes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62374:5"/> to divert his Reader, borrowing for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the witty Conceit of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Author of a little Book, Entituled, <hi>The Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſet in its True Light,</hi> p. 40. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, <hi>p.</hi> 19. he brings in a Catechumen, who deſires to know of the Biſhop what he underſtands by the Three of the Trinity; and ſeeing that the Biſhop avoids the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> he laughs at the Inſtruction which the Biſhop gives him, and leaves him to ſeek ſome comfort in the Doctrine of the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers. I am ſurprized that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo much trouble to prove, that the word <hi>Perſon</hi> occurs in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and in <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> ſince he ſhews himſelf, that the Biſhop believes as much as he does upon this Article, <hi>p.</hi> 17. The Biſhop had expreſſed himſelf very clearly upon the matter, <hi>p.</hi> 97. Theſe are his words, <q>This is the Doctrine that I intend now to explain to you: I do not mean that I will pretend to tell you how this is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and in what reſpect theſe Perſons are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be One, and in what reſpects they are Three.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> was reſolved to give his Suſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons a full ſcope, and he would rather rob the Biſhop of this Conſeſſion, than do him Juſtice by acknowledging the truth. All this ſavours very much of a Spirit of Diſputation, and argues but little ſincerity. But after all, it may be asked, why has not the Biſhop made uſe every where of the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> which is conſecrated by ſo long a Cuſtom in the Church, and why does he more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſay the Bleſſed Three? Any body elſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62374:5"/> but Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> would eaſily have apprehended the reaſon of it. The nature of the diſpute with <hi>Arians</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> who will have us ſtick to the words of Scripture, requires that we ſhould expreſs the truths of Chriſtianity in Scripture words, if we would have them to be received. If we at firſt daſh mingle with them words which they look upon as foreign, and which need to be ſoftned, to give them a ſenſe free from abſurdity in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Trinity; this ſerves only to render the Diſpute intricate, whereas we ſhould aim at the convincing of them by that principle which they acknowledge, namely the Authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>But there is ſomething more to be ſaid for the Biſhop. In all likelihood he would not engage himſelf in the Method of thoſe, who to defend the Doctrine of the Trinity againſt the <hi>Socinians,</hi> ſeem to have given them great Advantages by laying down Principles, from which it's to be feared oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion may be taken, to impute <hi>Tritheiſm</hi> to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the Trinity. This inconveniency may be avoided by reducing the diſpute to the terms of Scripture, which cannot ſo eaſily be done, when we employ ſuch words as are made uſe of by the <hi>Socinians</hi> againſt the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> to prove them guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Tritheiſm,</hi> which is juſtly look'd upon as the overthrowing of the whole Article of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>The Biſhop therefore, who himſelf uſes the word <hi>Perſon</hi> where he has occaſion for it, could have no manner of deſign to condemn that word, tho ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he abſtained from it; he only leaves it out of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62374:6"/> the Diſpute, that he might not involve himſelf into an unneceſſary Conteſt with relation to a <hi>Socinian.</hi> He has exactly kept himſelf to the terms of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which he thinks are preciſe enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince an <hi>Arian,</hi> or a <hi>Socinian.</hi> I am perſwaded, That if Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> had been to handle this Subject with the ſame views, he would have done as the Biſhop, and that no Biſhop would have cenſured him for it. But Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> was reſolved right or wrong, to appear in Publick againſt his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> comes on with a new Charge, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to faſten a ſuſpicion upon the Biſhop, as if he did not believe the perſonality of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> before the Incarnation. The Biſhop ſays, That the word <hi>Perſon</hi> was adopted, chiefly, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Patripaſſians.</hi> This does not ſatisfy Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> he labours to prove that <hi>Praxeas</hi> was the firſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that Hereſy; and he ſhews by St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, that the word <hi>Perſon</hi> was in uſe before <hi>Praxeas</hi>'s time. 'Tis not very material, and yet no Digreſſion, to ſhew that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> is miſtaken about the Antiquity of the <hi>Patripaſſians). Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> was the Author of that Sect, above 160 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Praxeas.</hi> At leaſt, this is what we are told by <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret. Vid. Cout. in lib. Conſtit. p.</hi> 285. Neither is it certain, that <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Character Hypoſtaſeos</hi> muſt be rendred by <hi>Perſon;</hi> the Vulgar has rendred it by <hi>Subſtance,</hi> as well as <hi>Chap.</hi> XI. And the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> have taken the word <hi>Hypoſtaſis</hi> in the <hi>Creed,</hi> for <hi>Eſſence</hi> or <hi>Subſtance.</hi> Thoſe who were at the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in the year 362. took it in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62374:6"/> ſame ſenſe; and St. <hi>Jerom</hi> underſtood it ſo, <hi>Ep.</hi> 57. However, ſays Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> the Biſhop has not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the <hi>Word</hi> the true Notion of a <hi>Perſon;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that he has avoided that Expreſſion in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. The Biſhop only acknowledges, That the Father, the <hi>Word,</hi> and the Spirit have a particular diſtinction from one another, by which every one of them differs from another; and tho Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> cites the Biſhop's words, who affirms, That in the Eſſence of God there are Three which are real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different from each other, and which differ from one another more than three Names, or three Economies, <hi>ad extra,</hi> or three Modes; yet he is not pleaſed with the Biſhop's Notion, but he muſt needs be a <hi>Sabellian.</hi> This Judgment is made too raſhly. The Biſhop ſays, That the word <hi>Perſon</hi> muſt not be underſtood in the matter of the Trinity, as we ordinarily do in relation to Creatures, <hi>a compleat Intelligent Being.</hi> And does this offend Mr. <hi>Hill?</hi> For my part, I can ſee no harm in it. The Biſhop has of his ſide all the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Divines, who have conſidered the Doctrine of the Trinity with ſome attention: For there is that difference betwixt the Perſons of the Trinity, and Perſons among Creatures, to which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of a <hi>Perſon,</hi> rejected by the Biſhop, does belong; that if that Definition were admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Trinity, it would import the Multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Eſſence, as well as the Multiplication of the Perſons, which is juſtly to be abhorred by all Divines. After all, if the Biſhop has not determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the nature and degree of the preciſe diſtinction which is betwixt the Three Perſons, but has adhered
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62374:7"/> in this matter, to what the Scripture teaches, he ought to be commended for his Modeſty, inſtead of being reproached for not having explained that which all prudent Divines own cannot be explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> himſelf knows well enough, that one cannot explain theſe differences, without either fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into difficulties, out of which he can't extricate himſelf, or aſſerting Contradictions which do much more weaken than Illuſtrate and confirm the belief of this Myſtery.</p>
            <p>Theſe are Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s chief Accuſations upon the Article of the Trinity. He has not been willing to conſider, as any equitable Man would have done, that the Biſhop did not deſign to write a Treatiſe upon the Trinity, which would have obliged him to handle this Subject in another manner, but that he glances only upon what muſt be ſaid in general, to be underſtood, in order to his treating of the Divinity of Chriſt, which is the only Subject-matter of his Diſcourſe. And ſince he briefly lays down the Article of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as a foundation to explain that of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, thoſe who after this can charge him with not believing the Trinity, becauſe he does not treat that matter in its full extent, muſt either be very malicious, or very defective in their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Let us come now to the point of the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. After that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> has ſuppoſed, contrary to all truth, that the Biſhop does not believe Three Perſons in the Trinity, he downright charges him with denying the Perſonality of the <hi>Word,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the Perſonality of the Meſſias no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62374:7"/> other way, than as the Perſonality of Jeſus Chriſt did reſult only from the Union of his Two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Then he gives himſelf a great deal of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to confute his own Whimſy. But I need on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remember him of the forecited words of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, to ſhew him how unfairly he deals in this matter. He does not act more honeſtly, when he wiredraws this Expreſſion of the Biſhop, <hi>That Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon in whom dwelt the Eternal Word,</hi> to prove that he acknowledges no Perſonality, but in the Humane Nature of Chriſt; Eſpecially, ſays he, becauſe the Biſhop has not exploded the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of thoſe, who conceive that the Character of <hi>Son of God</hi> has its foundation in the Humanity which the <hi>Word</hi> has aſſumed. The Biſhop has rejected this Notion as a falſe Doctrine, tho he has not refuted it <hi>ex profeſſo,</hi> his Subject lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to ſomething that was more material. But might not he ſpeak in the ſame ſtrain with all thoſe, who ſpeak of the Human Nature of Jeſus Chriſt? None elſe but Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> would have taken it amiſs. He muſt be ſtrangely given up to his Suſpicions, to conceive and publiſh ſuch as theſe againſt the Biſhop upon ſuch ſlight and poor Arguments. And does not Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> deſerve to be admired, when having criticized upon theſe words of the Biſhop, he obſerves, That ſince the Biſhop does not tell us, whether the Father, and the Spirit did enter into the Perſonality, which reſulted from the Union of the Two Natures, or not, but only that God and Man are become One Perſon, he has left a Door open for many Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies upon this Myſtery. One had need have much
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62374:8"/> patience to follow an Author ſo fruitful in vain Conceits. He quotes theſe words of the Biſhop, that the <hi>Word</hi> dwelt in Fleſh; and yet he is angry becauſe the Biſhop ſays elſewhere, that God and Man are become one Perſon; as if under the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral name of God, the Biſhop would leave his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to think that he underſtands the Father and the Spirit as well as the Word. At this rate when we ſay that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God, we leave the Hearer in ſuſpenſe, whether we mean that he is only the Son of the Father, or likewiſe the Son of the Holy Ghoſt. When a Man reaſons thus in a matter of ſo great moment, one would think he deſigns nothing elſe but to be laughed at, or to be read with indignation.</p>
            <p>He goes on to the Divinity of the Meſſias, upon which he raiſes new Accuſations againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; though he confeſſes <hi>p.</hi> 45. That the Biſhop has advanced many Good and Orthodox Truths upon this Article. This being the main thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the Biſhop, it will not be improper to give you a ſhort account of it, that you may judge the better of the Juſtice of Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Accuſations. Firſt of all the Biſhop gives an Idea of the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the <hi>Word</hi> in Fleſh; and he explains in a very intelligible manner, what's called in School-terms the <hi>Hypoſtatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> then he goes on to ſhew whence this Phraſe of Inhabitation, or <hi>Shekina</hi> is borrowed, namely, from the Divine Preſence, granted to the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Cloud of Glory which was over the Tabernacle. He very exactly obſerves, That the God of the <hi>Jews</hi> is called <hi>Jehovah,</hi> a word which the Seventy have rendred conſtantly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62374:8"/> by that of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles aſcribe conſtantly that word to Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe of the indwelling of the <hi>Word;</hi> ſo that when the Apoſtles have propoſed Jeſus Chriſt as the true Object of the Adoration of Chriſtians, they did not change the Object of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration received among the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſince it was the ſame <hi>Jehovah</hi> who inhabited before the Cloud of Glory, that now dwelt in Fleſh, in an inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable manner, which is to continue for ever. This is a ſhort abſtract of what the Biſhop explains at large, and with ſeveral reflections upon divers Texts of Scripture, <hi>p.</hi> 120. His words are; <q>In oppoſition to all which, we Chriſtians own but one ſupreme God, and we do alſo believe that this great God is alſo our federal God, or <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> by his dwelling in the Human Nature of Jeſus Chriſt; ſo that he is our Lord not by an aſſumption into high Dignity, or the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating divine Honour to him, but as the Eternal Word dwelt bodily in him: And thus he is our Lord, not as a Being diſtinct from, or deputed by the great God, but as the great God manifeſting himſelf in his Fleſh or human Nature; which is the great Myſtery of Godlineſs, or of true Religion: And this will give a clear account of all thoſe other paſſages of the New Teſtament, in which the Lord Jeſus is mentioned, as diſtinct from, and ſubordinate to God and his Father. The one is the more extended Notion of God, as the Maker and Preſerver of all things; and the other is the more ſpecial Notion, as appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62374:9"/> to Chriſtians, by which God is federally their God, Lord, or <hi>Jehovah.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly a Man muſt have a ſmall ſtock of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty or Sincerity, who having read this Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, can charge a Prelate with Socinianiſm, or Neſtorianiſm. And thus he goes about to prove his accuſation. He takes notice of an Expreſſion of the Biſhop's, <hi>p.</hi> 25. We believe, ſays the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, That Chriſt was God by vertue of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling of the eternal <hi>Word</hi> in him; the <hi>Jews</hi> could make no Objection to this, who knew that their Fathers had worſhipped the Cloud of Glory, becauſe of God's reſting upon it. It is a fine thing to ſee how gravely Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſnaps up this Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> worſhipping the <hi>Shekina:</hi> Here he makes a pompous ſhew of needleſs Remarks, to convince the Biſhop that God and the Cloud were two different things; and that the <hi>Jews</hi> never worſhipped the Cloud of Glory, becauſe otherwiſe they had been Idolaters. And all this, becauſe the Biſhop has taken the <hi>Shekina,</hi> for God dwelling in the Cloud. I confeſs that Expreſſion is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether exact; but a candid Reader would eaſily have underſtood it by ſo many other Expreſſions which the Biſhop employs in ſpeaking upon this Subject, where he ſhews the difference which he makes between God and the Cloud of Glory. No body has found fault with Dr. <hi>Teniſon</hi> for taking the <hi>Shekina</hi> for the ſecond Perſon, (of Idolatry <hi>p.</hi> 319.) theſe are his words; <q>Accordingly when God is ſaid in the Old Teſtament to have appeared, they ſeem to miſtake, who aſcribe it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62374:9"/> to an Angel perſonating God, and not to the ſecond Perſon, as the <hi>Shekina</hi> (or as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calleth him) the repreſentator of the Father. The ſame Expreſſion occurs <hi>p.</hi> 380. of the ſame Book.</q> And yet Dr. <hi>Teniſon</hi> has not been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hitherto of confounding the Habitation, with the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that dwelt in the Cloud. Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> ſays as much as Dr. <hi>Teniſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> does not take it ill. He has read <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Book againſt <hi>Praxeas,</hi> but he ſeems not to have underſtood that Maxim in it. —<hi>Malo te ad ſenſum rei, quam ad ſonum vocabuli exerceas;</hi> at leaſt he does not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it much in reſpect to the Biſhop; eſpecially ſince he owns, <hi>p.</hi> 27. that the Biſhop has corrected that Expreſſion. But Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> does not only at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack this Expreſſion, which though in it ſelf it may be ſomewhat improper, is yet uſual enough; but he falls upon the whole Argument of the Biſhop; and to overthrow it, he denies in the firſt place what the Biſhop advances, That the word <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi> has been always applied to the Divinity dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Cloud of Glory. Secondly, Though this were granted, he denies, That the Divinity of the Meſſias can be inferred from <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s dwelling bodily in him, as the Biſhop would have it. And he does not believe that St. <hi>Paul, Col.</hi> 2. has furniſhed the Biſhop with a notion of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity's dwelling in Jeſus Chriſt, ſufficient to ground Adoration upon. Laſtly, He accuſes the Biſhop of not having fully anſwered a difficulty which he propoſes to himſelf from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. which ſeems to appropriate the name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to the Son excluſively of the Father; and he gives
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62374:10"/> us another Solution which he thinks is better. We ſhall reſume every one of theſe Heads in their order. And,</p>
            <p n="1">I. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> denies that the word <hi>Jehovah</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways aſcribed to God, with relation to this Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation in the Cloud. What tho the Biſhop had been ſomewhat too poſitive concerning the word <hi>Jehovah,</hi> in aſſerting that it always refers to the Habitation in the Cloud? Here were after all no great harm, ſince Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> himſelf owns that he is called ſo where ſpoken of as in Covenant with the <hi>Jews.</hi> A little Candor and Common Senſe would have prompted an Ingenuous Reader to make that Reſtriction of the Biſhop's words; but in vain ſhould the Biſhop look for ſo much Equity from Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> who diſputes for diſputing's ſake. Divines of a greater Name than Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> laugh at thoſe Remarks which he has accumulated. Dr. <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon</hi> has proved, That the <hi>Shekina</hi> is celebrated down from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> from <hi>Noah</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> from <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Captivity, and from the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity to the <hi>Meſſias.</hi> This is in his Book of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where one would think he intended a Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Mr. <hi>Hill.</hi> After all, whatever the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word <hi>Jehovah</hi> may have been before the Law, it's certain, as I ſaid, That under the Law that word denoted the God which the <hi>Jews</hi> worſhipped in the Cloud of Glory, and that it is with reſpect to that Habitation that St. <hi>John</hi> ſays, ſpeaking of his Incarnation, That the Word has dwelt amongſt us. The Biſhop, who intends to prove that the Apoſtles did not propoſe another Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62374:10"/> of Adoration, than the <hi>Jehovah</hi> worſhipped under the Law, deſires no more than this, which is ſufficient for his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But can we rationally infer the Adoration of the Meſſias from this, that the fulneſs of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head dwells in him bodily, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us? <hi>Col.</hi> 2. The Orthodox have believed it to this day, and the Biſhop with them; but out of ſpight to the Biſhop, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> will not allow this to be a good conſequence; he does not much concern himſelf, whether the <hi>Socinians</hi> triumph or not, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he may quarrel with the Biſhop, by alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I know not what frivolous Exceptions, of which himſelf would have been aſhamed, had he not been tranſported with his Paſſion. To take this paſſage from the Biſhop which ſeems ſo full to his purpoſe, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> gives it ſo Chimerical an Interpretation, that probably he is the firſt Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of it; he pretends that the Apoſtle ſpeaks there in oppoſition to the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> Notions, who excluded Jeſus Chriſt from the Supreme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Divinity; but that tho St. <hi>Paul</hi> had declared <hi>Jehovah</hi> to be in Jeſus Chriſt, yet of what ſort of inexiſtence ſoever this might be underſtood, it could not be concluded from it, that the Meſſias was to be adored. I am not of Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s mind concerning the ſenſe he gives to the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in that place of St. <hi>Paul.</hi> 'Tis not very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that this Apoſtle had an eye to the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> and it is much more natural to underſtand this fulneſs in oppoſition to the Manifeſtations of the Deity under the <hi>Old Teſtament;</hi> the Sequel of the Diſcourſe ſeems to lead us thither, ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62374:11"/> declares that it dwelt bodily, which is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Figures. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the word which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle has expreſſed by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies really and ſubſtantially. But be this as it will, what can Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> mean, when he denies that from ſuch an Habitation as this, by which the Fleſh is perſonally united to the Deity, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of the Meſſias cannot be inferred? It's plain, that the Biſhop does not pretend that the Fleſh ought to be adored in the Perſon of Jeſus Chriſt; but it is yet more certain, that no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrian, except thoſe that deny the Hypoſtatical Union of both Natures, denies that the word in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate is to be adored, that is, the Meſſias, who is God and Man. They all agree, That the Principle of <hi>Adorability,</hi> or that for which the Perſon of the Meſſias is to be adored, is the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Word; but they don't deny, as Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſeems to do, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Object of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, becauſe the indwelling of the Word is ſuch, that thereby the Human and Divine Natures are united in one Perſonality.</p>
            <p>Here is another Criticiſm of Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s. He owns, That the Argument which the Biſhop draws from the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is conſtantly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Jeſus Chriſt in the <hi>New,</hi> and anſwers to that of <hi>Jehovah</hi> in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Argument, but he thinks the Biſhop had not skill enough to free it from an Objection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. The <hi>Arians</hi> have inſiſted upon that place, Verſe 6. <hi>Nobis tamen unus Deus pater,</hi> to prove that the Son was not God. They have been anſwered, That when the Father is named here,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62374:11"/> the Son is alſo evidently ſuppoſed, as having the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, if he be truly the Son of God. It has been often ſaid to them, that by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we might conclude, That the Father is not <hi>Dominus,</hi> becauſe the Apoſtle adds, <hi>&amp; unus Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Jeſus Chriſtus pèr quem omnia;</hi> and wherein has the Biſhop enervated this Argument? Becauſe the Biſhop affirms (ſays Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>) that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> anſwering to that of <hi>Jehovah</hi> in the Seventy Tranſlation, is here appropriated to Jeſus Chriſt, which he eſtabliſhes as a conſequence of his Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis, that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a federal Title of God, with relation to the <hi>Jews.</hi> Now Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> thinks that's a falſe Hypotheſis: On the other hand he pretends, That the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to that of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which cannot be rendred by <hi>Jehovae</hi> in the Plural Number; from whence he concludes, That the Biſhop has not taken off the Objection he makes to himſelf. The queſtion ſtarted by Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> whether the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> expreſſes that of <hi>Jehovah;</hi> and whether ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it expreſſes the <hi>Jehovah</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> it is a federal word with reſpect to the <hi>Jews;</hi> this queſtion, I ſay, is decided in favour of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, not only by the Moderns, but alſo by the Ancients. If Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> has a mind to be inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Opinion of the Ancients in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matter, let him read <hi>Origen</hi> upon the 8th of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel, p.</hi> 1. and St. <hi>Jerom</hi> upon the ſame at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his 9th Book; he may read alſo the Learned <hi>Pearſon</hi> upon the Creed, as to the ſecond thing controverted here between the Biſhop and him. The foundation of this Opinion is more
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62374:12"/> ſolid than Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> is aware of; almoſt all the Ancients prove the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was he who appeared under the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament;</hi> and that he who then appeared is named <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which the Seventy render by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Therefore the Apoſtle might ſay, according to this Phraſeology, that if the Chriſtians did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge but one God, they acknowledge like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but one Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt; giving to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Title of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which is rendred by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi> So that it is St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrine, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Incarnate is no leſs <hi>Jehovah</hi> than he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Incarnation. If it were otherwiſe, St. <hi>Paul</hi> had argued like a Sophiſter, when he proves by a paſſage out of <hi>Joel,</hi> that Salvation belongs to Chriſtians, becauſe they invoke Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Lord ſpoken of in <hi>Joel, Rom.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>I know not why Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> is not ſatisfied with this Solution; 'tis his fault, and not the Biſhop's: For whoever aſſerts that St. <hi>Paul</hi> finds the Fountain of the Diety in the Father, by reaſon of which he calls the Father the only God, and whoever maintains that the Son is the ſecond Perſon, who is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by the <hi>Jews,</hi> and by whom God has acted all along during that Oeconomy, leaves no force at all to the Objections of <hi>Arians</hi> or <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> rejects the Argument for our Saviour's Divinity, which the Biſhop draws from this; that we don't read either in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> or in their <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> that ever the <hi>Jews</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62374:12"/> did object to <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that they were guilty of Idolatry; this Argument ſeems to him falſe and impertinet. 'Tis ſtrange how men are ſometimes blinded by Paſſion, and carried away with the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſs of Diſputing! The Biſhop does not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue here againſt all ſorts of men, but only againſt the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who maintain that Jeſus Chriſt was exalted to the Title of God after his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. It's certain, that in this caſe the ſilence of the <hi>Jews</hi> is a very ſtrange thing, for they would not have failed to object againſt Chriſtians, that their Religion did propoſe a new Divinity, altogether unkown under the Law. On the other hand, if this objection was ever made againſt the Chriſtians, 'tis very ſtrange likewiſe, that the Apoſtles ſhould no where obviate the Scandal which the <hi>Jews</hi> might ſo juſtly have taken at that new object of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip, which they propoſed. I don't know how Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> is made, but I am ſure that a <hi>Socinian</hi> could never make uſe of thoſe Anſwers which he furniſhes him with: At leaſt, if I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member well, the <hi>Scocinian</hi> who has Anſwered his Lordſhip, has thought fitter to ſay nothing upon this Argument of the Biſhop, than to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Solutions, which he has not judged to be a ſolid and ſufficient Anſwer to this Obſervation of the Biſhop.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> having thus cenſured what the Biſhop ſays concerning the Trinity and the Incarnation, one would have thought that he was going to enter upon the Examination of thoſe Cenſures which the Biſhop has made of the Fathers in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; but he returns to the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62374:13"/> and accuſes the Biſhop of having ſuppreſſed the Notions which diſtinguiſh the Perſons; <hi>viz.</hi> Generation and Proceſſion.</p>
            <p>This Accuſation is as unjuſt and as ill grounded as all the reſt; for the Biſhop ſays enough of that Matter, <hi>p.</hi> 132, 133, and 134. He ſhould have conſidered, that ſince the Biſhop did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a Treatiſe concerning the Trinity, he was not bound to examine the whole Dogma; it was enough for his purpoſe to mention only what he thought moſt fit to eſtabliſh the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Chriſt, that he intended to prove againſt the <hi>Socinians.</hi> Beſides, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ought to have done the Biſhop the Juſtice to believe, that he does no leſs include in the Myſtery (which he does not pretend to explain for fear of deſtroying the nature of it) thoſe Notions which diſtinguiſh the Perſons, than the Dogma it ſelf. And indeed, though theſe Notions which the Biſhop owns to be ſo real, as to produce a real and numerical di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction betwixt the Perſons, are uſed by us in ſpeaking of the Trinity, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that they are no leſs Myſterious and Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to be explained than the Dogma it ſelf. We underſtand what made Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> return to this Subject; he had a mind to bring in queſtion the Biſhop's believing of the Trinity, becauſe he ſays in a Letter to Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> that in many ancient Manuſcripts he has not found that celebrated place of St. <hi>John, There are three,</hi> &amp;c. Here he oppoſes to the Biſhop an Author who takes this place for Genuine; this is no great piece of Cunning. For neither the Biſhop, nor the other learned men,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62374:13"/> who compare the Manuſcripts upon controverted places, do thereby give the Hereticks any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Dr. <hi>Fell,</hi> the late Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> who took ſo much pains in this kind of Literature, would have thanked the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> for his Diſcovery: For that great Man judged of things otherways, and by more elevated Principles than Mr. <hi>Hill.</hi> I am ſure Dr. <hi>Mills</hi> will make uſe of the Biſhop's Obſervation, and do him that Juſtice which the Biſhop of <hi>Oxford</hi> would have done, if he had executed his Deſign. But this keeps me from the main Subject.</p>
            <p>Let us ſee at laſt what Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> cenſures in the Biſhop, concerning his pretended ill uſage of the Fathers, <hi>p.</hi> 51. He taxes the Fathers, ſays Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> 
               <q>for no real Obliquities, but their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Principles; fixes on them ſuch Theories as they never dreamed of, and ſuch as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of their own avowed Faith; and this without quoting ſo much as one paſſage out of them; he gives them not ſo much as one good word, but finally preſents them to us as a parcel of impertinent and ſelf-contradictory Bablers.</q> Here is the Charge, and the Proof follows, <hi>p.</hi> 54. In this, ſays the Biſhop, <hi>i. e.</hi> in their teaching the Reſpects and Modes of this Unity and Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, too many both Ancients and Moderns have, perhaps, gone beyond bounds, while ſome were pleaſed with the Platonical Notions of Emana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Fecundity in the Divine Eſſence. The Biſhop, you ſee, uſes the words <hi>perhaps</hi> and <hi>too many,</hi> he does not ſay all; which does mightily
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62374:14"/> mitigate his Aſſertion. And yet Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſay, That he reflects upon the whole An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church before and after the Council of <hi>Nice:</hi> This is not very ſincere. But granting the Biſhop had ſpoken ſo generally as Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes it to him, yet he had ſaid nothing upon this Matter, but what many learned men of both Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions have advanced. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſays, That we may very well aſcribe Platonical Notions to <hi>Arius,</hi> ſince <hi>Petavius</hi> avers that <hi>Arius</hi> was a Platoniſt; but not to the Fathers who have diſputed againſt <hi>Arius.</hi> This matter of Fact is not ſo certain as Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> thinks. Doctor <hi>Cudworth</hi> pretends that <hi>Petavius</hi> is miſtaken, and that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and the Fathers of <hi>Nice</hi> were much greater Platoniſts than <hi>Arius.</hi> But without entring upon that Queſtion, it's undeniably true that the Fathers have made uſe of <hi>Plato</hi>'s Authority to explain the Myſtery of the Trinity.<note place="margin">Juſtin. M. Ap. 2. p. 93. B. C.</note> 
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus, Origen,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis,</hi> have done it before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice;</hi> and St. <hi>Cyril</hi> does the ſame after them againſt <hi>Julian.</hi> And yet Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> comes and tells us poſitively, that the Fathers were not Platoniſts, becauſe <hi>Petavius</hi> ſays that <hi>Arius</hi> was a Platoniſt. <hi>Petavius</hi> acknowledges that <hi>Plato</hi>'s Trinity does very widely differ from the Chriſtian Trinity. Doctor <hi>Teniſon</hi> ſays the ſame, and proves it with great Exactneſs and Learning (of Idolatry, <hi>p.</hi> 77, 78, and <hi>p.</hi> 139.) And after this, Is it a Crime for the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> to reject thoſe Platonical Notions of the Trinity?</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62374:14"/>
            <p>But after all, ſays Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> The Doctrine of Emanations is derived from the School of the <hi>Jews</hi> before Jeſus Chriſt, and applied by the Fathers to the Doctrine of the Trinity; and the Biſhop ought not to have ſuppoſed that ſome of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients did reject them, while they were admitted by others. This Accuſation may be refuted in a word. The Biſhop himſelf admits of Emanations, as giving us the propereſt Idea to expreſs what we conceive of the Trinity; but he rejects the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonical Emanations, which have no manner of Conformity with the Trinity of Chriſtians, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many Ancients and Moderns have adopted them, as all the learned do acknowledge.</p>
            <p>I ſhall make the ſame Anſwer concerning Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundity, whereof Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> thinks the Biſhop has avoided the Notion in explaining the Trinity. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> grows ſo exceeding warm upon this Point, That he pronounces <hi>Anathema</hi> againſt the Biſhop if he does not acknowledge it. But why ſo much Noiſe? The Biſhop employs his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in proving the Divinity of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to whom the Father has communicated the Divine Nature; this is what we call Eternal Generation: So that he can't be ſaid abſolutely to deny the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundity of the Divine Nature, which conſiſts in that it is communicated to ſeveral perſons. But he does not believe Fecundity, according to the common Notion implied in that word, and which ſeems to import that the Son muſt beget as well as the Father, having the ſame Nature in himſelf; and if he denys this Fecundity, with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62374:15"/> relation to the Holy Ghoſt, Muſt he be therefore ſtruck with <hi>Anathema?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word Fecundity may be uſed in a good Senſe, in ſpeaking of the Generation of the Son, which is the communication of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the Father to the Son; but I queſtion whether it may be uſed with reſpect to the Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>a Patre &amp; a Filio;</hi> this Emanation is never called Generation in Scripture, the Language whereof ſhould be our Rule in ſpeaking of this Myſtery; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſome Divines may have thought, it is more prudent to abſtain from it. The Nominals main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that it is as true to ſay, <hi>Deus non generat,</hi> which is true in regard of the Son, as to ſay, <hi>Deus generat,</hi> which is true of the Father. I would fain know Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Opinion about this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Voluntas genuit voluntatem, ut ſapientia genuit ſapientiam.</hi> I am perſuaded he would not like it, though it is certainly true that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> have carried thus far the Notion of Fecundity.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> fancies to Nonplus the Biſhop, when he charges him with aſcribing to the Fathers ſuch Notions as were altogether Heatheniſh, and even ſaying, that they introduced them into the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, which has, <hi>Lumen de lumine,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Eternal Word.</hi> Theſe are the Biſhop's words, <hi>p.</hi> 61. <q>For we have footſteps of a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as Ancient as any we can trace up, which limited the Emanations to Three. And theſe thought there was a production, or rather
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62374:15"/> an Eduction of two out of the firſt, in the ſame manner that ſome Philoſophers thought that Souls were propagated from Souls; and the Figure by which this was explained, being that of one Candle being lighted at another, this ſeems to have given the riſe to thoſe words <hi>Light of Light.</hi> It is certain that many of the Fathers fell often into this conceit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> From theſe words Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> concludes, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Fathers, according to the Biſhop, have borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Notion of the Three Emanations, from that of the Philoſophers touching the Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Souls, namely, the Notion of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of Souls <hi>ex traduce. Secondly,</hi> He pretends that the Fathers did never uſe that ſimile of two Candles, whereof one is lighted by the other. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He charges him with fixing a Platonick, <hi>i. e.</hi> a Pagan Notion upon that <hi>Nicene</hi> Article. <hi>Light of Light.</hi> All this <hi>Criticiſm,</hi> which takes up about thirty Pages, may be reduced to nothing in a few words.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>Firſt,</hi> nothing is more certain, than that <hi>Tatian, Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s Diſciple, has the Similitude of a Torch or Candle lighting another. <q>Cum voluit Deus, <hi>ſays he, p. 145.</hi> verbum ex ejus ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitate proſilicit, &amp; verbum non inaniter prolatum, primogenitum opus fit ipſius ſpiritus. Hoc ſcimus autem eſſe principium Mundi, Natum eſt autem, non per diviſionem, non peravulſionem; quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum enim ab una face permultae accenduntur, nec tamen primae facis lux minuitur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62374:16"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 145. B. and this Similitude they ſeem to have borrowed from <hi>Philo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de ſignal. p. 223. F.</note> who ſpeaking of the Spirit imparted from <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Seventy Elders, ſaith this was not done, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by Abſciſſion, but as Fire is lighted from Fire, or one Taper from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without Diminution of its light, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">Dial. cum Tryph. p. 358. B. C. D.</note> or at leaſt, from his Maſter <hi>Juſtin,</hi> who ſaith, that in Explication of this matter he uſed this Example, rather than that of the Light of the Sun. 'Tis plain, That the Fathers have built on this bottom, when they made uſe of the Similitude of the Sun,<note place="margin">Athenago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus Tertullian &amp; Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</note> and its Beams. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Biſhop might have proved very well by the Teſtimonies of <hi>Juſtin</hi> and <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> that the Ancients had not a very juſt Idea of the Doctrine of the Trinity, when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived two Generations of the <hi>Word;</hi> the one <hi>ab aeterno;</hi> the other before the Creation of the World; the one by which the <hi>Word</hi> is only as <hi>in potentia,</hi> in the Father; the other by which he is actually produced by the Will of the Father, <hi>cum voluit Deus,</hi> ſays <hi>Tatian,</hi> p. 145. This Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem was alſo followed by <hi>Theophilus</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Athenagoras.</hi> This is but a light Error in thoſe Ancients, if we believe Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> who ſays, That this Syſtem was never condemned in the Church, tho it was never made or eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a neceſſary Point of Faith or Doctrine, <hi>p.</hi> 75.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62374:16"/> What a buſtle would Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> have kept, if the Biſhop had advanced the like Propoſition? I'm afraid a Judicious Reader will be tempted to think, when he ſees this ſeverity of Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> towards the Biſhop, and his great Indulgence to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, that he has two Weights and two Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. For after all, the Biſhop's reaſons to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Syſtem of the Ancients, are much more ſolid than thoſe by which Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> endavours to ſoften and excuſe it. 'Tis in vain for Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> to aſſert that this Syſtem is not Platonical, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Juſtin</hi> had renounced <hi>Plato</hi>'s Philoſophy: I can tell him that that Syſtem is much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to that of <hi>Plato,</hi> than to Scripture; and in fact, it was laid aſide in the Controverſy with the <hi>Arians,</hi> who drew great advantages from it. Thus ſome other <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> of the Ancients were rejected, as that of the Inviſibility of the Father, and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of the Son.</p>
            <p>In fine, let it be granted to Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> that the Fathers of <hi>Nice</hi> have borrowed the Article, <hi>Light of Light,</hi> from the Platoniſts Notion, and that the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> does affirm it; pray where is the Crime of that? Was not the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the Heathens? If this Notion which was common to Scripture, with the wiſeſt Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, could be uſefully employed to denote that the Divine Eſſence is in the Father, and in the Son, as Light is of the ſame Nature in two Candles, one of which is lighted by the other; why ſhould not they have made uſe of it? This is <hi>Tatian</hi>'s Notion, and the learned Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62374:17"/> that the Fathers of <hi>Nice</hi> have followed the ſame, <hi>p.</hi> 60. <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis</hi> drew the Scheme of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed; and it appears by his Book, <hi>De Praeparatione Evangelica,</hi> how much ſtreſs he laid upon <hi>Plato</hi>'s Authority to eſtabliſh the Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma of the Trinity. The Fathers of the Council added only to it the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which at firſt ſeemed hard to <hi>Euſebius,</hi> but he admitted it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. This word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> had been diſgraced by the abuſe that <hi>Paulus Samoſathenus</hi> made of it, having employed it to denote that Jeſus Chriſt was only of the ſame Nature with us: But the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of <hi>Nice</hi> have uſed it to ſignify, that he was of the ſame Nature with the eternal Father. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> have made uſe of it, in the firſt Senſe, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Faith of the Church againſt the <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linarians</hi> and <hi>Eutichians,</hi> who denied that Jeſus Chriſt had a Soul. No man has found fault with him for making that uſe of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. If <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis</hi> had not been the firſt Author of this Creed, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Objection would be of ſome force. But as it is certain, that the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers have uſed the Creed, drawn up by <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius Caeſarienſis,</hi> without adding any thing elſe to it, but the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and the Condemnation of <hi>Arius</hi>'s Propoſitions confirming the Condemnation pronounced before by <hi>Alexander;</hi> ſo it is viſible that they have made uſe of a Notion in it, which was received by thoſe Fathers that were Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts: It ſeemed to them conſonant to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith; and we receive it at this Day, taking
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62374:17"/> it in a commodious Senſe; I ſay we take it in a large Senſe; for it is certain that this Expreſſion <hi>Deus de Deo,</hi> being as ſtrictly taken as Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> uſually takes words in Diſputing againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, does rather denote the Subſtance than the Perſonality, as that of <hi>Lumen de Lumine;</hi> and when in pronouncing theſe words we refer them to the Perſonality, we have more regard to the Senſe of the Church, than to the natural Import and Signification of the Expreſſion; for we only mean that the Son is derived from the Father, who communicates the Divine Eſſence to him, and not that the Eſſence of the Father's Divinity produces ſuch another Eſſence in the Son.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> might very well have forborn his Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the Biſhop upon this Article of the Creed; for whatever pains he takes to deliver his Readers from this thought, that the Fathers of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice</hi> have referred the Expreſſion <hi>Deus de Deo, &amp; Lumen de Lumine,</hi> to the ſecond Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet he himſelf furniſhes us with a ſufficient Argument to confute him, in the paſſages which he quotes in the Margin out of <hi>Tertullian, Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Athenagoras, Juſtin</hi> and <hi>Tatian.</hi> For the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have uſed theſe Expreſſions with <hi>Tertullian</hi> againſt <hi>Praxeas,</hi> to denote the ſecond, but not the eternal Generation of the <hi>Word. Tertullian</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly called the ſecond Generation the true Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of the Word. What can a Reader con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from thence, but that the Notion <hi>Deus de Deo, &amp; Lumen de Lumine,</hi> in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> relates to this ſecond Generation? Which Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> himſelf calls an odd Conceit, <hi>p.</hi> 12. though he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62374:18"/> affirms, <hi>p.</hi> 75. that the Church never condemned it: So that upon the whole Matter, it is very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to believe that the Fathers of <hi>Nice</hi> took theſe words in the ſame Senſe in which they were taken by the Ancients.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> may ſee now of what uſe the Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Notions have been to explain the Doctrine of the Trinity. The learned confeſs that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Plato,</hi> and his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> have nothing common with the two laſt Perſons of the Trinity. This is not only acknowledged, but proved by the learned Dr. <hi>Teniſon,</hi> in the Book before cited. On the other hand, it's no leſs certain that the Ancients have made uſe of the Platonick Notions, upon the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſhew that <hi>Plato</hi> owned the two laſt Perſons of the Trinity. What follows from all this, but that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> might have ſpared his Cenſures againſt the Biſhop? And that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his endeavours, all what he has ſaid to juſtify the Ancients, is uſeleſs and inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add but one word more upon this Head; <hi>viz.</hi> That it does not become Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> to find fault with the Biſhop for having aſſerted that the Fathers before the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> did conceive in the Trinity a Subordination, importing an inequality of the two laſt Perſons with the firſt: He will give himſelf a very needleſs trouble if he undertake to clear them from that. The Biſhop has but too many Proofs upon this Article; and none but thoſe who never read the Ancients, or read them without attention, can diſown it. This
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62374:18"/> is acknowledged by <hi>Petavius,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> and <hi>Heuetius, Origen, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 2. By this kind of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicious Accuſations Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> would almoſt tempt a man to draw ſuch a Picture of Antiquity, as would not be much to its advantage. We may ſay in a word, That if there have been ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Ancients who have recommended the ſtudy of Pagan Authors, becauſe of the uſe that a Chriſtian might make of them, to render the Doctrines of his Religion more probable to the Heathens, there have been others who have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt abſolutely condemned that ſtudy, ſeeing what impreſſion Platoniſm had made in the Minds of the Primitive Chriſtians; ſo that Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> was in the right, in the <hi>Roman</hi> Council, when he ranked with prohibited Books the greateſt part of thoſe Authors who have ſpoken ſo crudely upon the point of the Trinity.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> proceeds to another Accuſation, which is as ill grounded: He pretends that the Biſhop has unjuſtly charged the Fathers with believing a ſpecifick Unity of the Divine Eſſence, and with having underſtood the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in that Senſe, <hi>p.</hi> 91. and <hi>ſeq.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> thinks this is to charge the Fathers with Tritheiſm, which he may with ſo much the more reaſon impute to the Biſhop; that the Biſhop ſuppoſing that the Fathers have attributed to the Perſons Operations <hi>ad extra,</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from each other; he is not only fallen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the ſame Notion, but which is more, he has inſinuated, by his method, that he believes a <hi>Tetras</hi> in God, namely the Eſſence <hi>in abſtracto,</hi> and the three Perſons. I ſay this is a very ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62374:19"/> Accuſation; for it's true that there are but too many of the Ancients who have gone upon this Hypotheſis the Biſhop ſpeaks of, in explaining the Dogma of the Trinity. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> may be informed of it by reading amongſt others Father <hi>Petav. de S. Trinit. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 9. The Learned Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> has ſaid as much as the Biſhop; theſe are his words, <hi>Intellect. Syſt. p.</hi> 604. <q>However it is evident from hence, that theſe reputed Orthodox Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who were not a few, were far from think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the three Hypoſtaſes of the Trinity to have the ſame ſingular exiſtent Eſſence; they ſuppoſing 'em to have no otherwiſe one and the ſame Eſſence of the Godhead in them, nor to be one God, than three individual men have one common ſpecifical Eſſence of Manhood in them, and are all one Man. But as this Trinity came after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to be decried for Tritheiſm; ſo in the room thereof ſtarted thereup that other Trinity of Perſons numerically the ſame, or having all one and the ſame ſingular exiſtent Eſſence; a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which ſeeemeth not to have been owned by any publick Authority in the Chriſtian Church, ſave that of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council only.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I know there are ſome learned men, who, as Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> have endeavoured to give a good Senſe to their Expreſſions, and by a long compaſs of Conſequences reduce them to the ordinary No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. We cannot but commend their Zeal for Antiquity; but after all, it were expedient that thoſe who have the Opinions of the Fathers but at the ſecond hand, ſhould not be ſo poſitive in juſtifying all their Sentiments. Thoſe who are
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62374:19"/> troubled it thoſe failings with which the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be charged, ought to conſider; <hi>Firſt,</hi> That without examining Queſtions with great care, it is not poſſible to foreſee all the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that may be drawn from them. <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> That theſe Queſtions have riſen one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in proceſs of time, and of many Diſputes. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That it eaſily happens, even to thoſe who handle Matters with the greateſt caution, to fall into Expreſſions, which being ſtrictly taken, have a harſh Senſe. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That the Authority of ſome great men has often gained to them great numbers of Followers, concerning things which Poſterity has juſtly condemned. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That almoſt all the ſtrayings of the Fathers do riſe from thence; that in combating the Hereticks they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the ſimplicity of Scripture Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and undertook to explain this Myſtery by human Ideas very remote from the Truth.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> tells us, The Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> who imputes to the Fathers a ſort of <hi>Tritheiſm</hi> by his Explanation, falls himſelf into the ſame Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity; nay, he eſtabliſhes a kind of <hi>Tetras</hi> in the Godhead, which is worſe than <hi>Tritheiſm.</hi> This is a great Charge. In the Divine Eſſence, ſays the Biſhop, there may be Three that may have a diverſity of Operations as well as oeconomies. Here is the hereſy of theſe words, according to Mr. <hi>Hill, p.</hi> 98. Now, whatſoever acts by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is diſtinct from that other by which it acts, if prior in the Agency, by the order of reaſon. Here we have indeed a ſpecial Hunter of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks: I ſhall not anſwer him, that there have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62374:20"/> been divers Schoolmen who believed an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Subſiſtence of the Divine Eſſence, beſides the three Subſiſtences, which make the Perſonalities, without acknowledging that <hi>Tetras</hi> that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſpeaks of; the Biſhop, I am ſure, would not uſe this Apology; But I anſwer, That he offers a manifeſt violence to the Biſhop's words, that contains nothing but what is agreeable to the conſtant way of ſpeaking which Divines uſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Operations appropriated to each Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, without confounding them with the notio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Expreſſions that ſerve to diſtinguiſh them. The Name of God ſometimes ſignifies his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſometimes the Three Perſons; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it imports but One Perſon of the Trinity; do we therefore acknowledge a Quaternity? To draw ſuch conſequences as theſe in order to aſcribe Hereſies to thoſe who ſometimes uſe the Word GOD in one of theſe ſignifications, and ſometimes in another, is meer Sophiſtry. We ſay, That the Father is God, to denote his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence: We ſay, That God has created the World, to expreſs the common Work of the Trinity: We ſay, That God is incarnate, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the Union of the <hi>Word</hi> with Humanity. How many Hereſies might be imputed to Writers, if one would make ſuch Objections againſt them, and urge upon the word GOD Notions altogether fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to the Subject in hand? But God be thanked, that all thoſe who write, are not of Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s temper.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> follows his blow; after he has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached the Biſhop for repreſenting the Ancients as Tritheiſts, he accuſes him of maintaining that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62374:20"/> thoſe who ſucceeded them, have uſed Notions that were little better, when they made uſe of that Notion of the Sun, with its Light and Heat; and of that of the Soul, from whence flows the Underſtanding and the Will, to expreſs the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of the Trinity. Nay, he objects to him, that thoſe who have ſuppoſed different Operations in the Two Perſons, are, according to this Syſtem, as much Tritheiſts as the firſt. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> affirms on the contrary, That theſe Notions of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which the Biſhop rejects, have been uſed from the beginning; ſo that the Biſhop ought not to have ſaid, that the uſing of theſe Notions was only that the Fathers might get out of <hi>Tritheiſm.</hi> This is a very pitiful Accuſation. It ſeems Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> did not underſtand the Biſhop's meaning, when he ſays that the Emanation of the Son and Holy Ghoſt were expreſſed by the acts of Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Will; he does not intend to deny, that this Notion was uſed in ancient Times, but only to condemn the boldneſs of the Schoolmen, who would almoſt make this way of explaining the Proceſſion of the Perſons, paſs for an Article of Faith, namely, that the Son proceeds by the Underſtanding, and the Holy Ghoſt by the Will; tho very Eminent Divines have rejected theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions, as <hi>Zanchius lib.</hi> 5. <hi>C. ultimo,</hi> and <hi>Duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> refutes them in 1. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 6. <hi>q.</hi> 2. As to what Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> fancies, that the Biſhop is guilty of <hi>Tritheiſm,</hi> becauſe he aſcribes different Operations to the Two Perſons; the poor man is viſibly miſtaken. Does not all Divines acknowledge different Operations of the Two Perſons? Are they thereby infected with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62374:21"/> 
               <hi>Tritheiſm?</hi> Or was St. <hi>Paul</hi> infected with Hereſy, when he ſaid, <hi>There are diverſities of gifts, but the ſame ſpirit; there are differences of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but the ſame Lord; there are diverſities of operations, but it is the ſame God, who worketh all in all,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.4, 5, 6. I ſee what led Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> into this Error. He did imagine that, becauſe it is a Maxim in Divinity, that the Actions of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity <hi>ad extra,</hi> are common to the Three Perſons, there are no Actions particularly belonging to One Perſon, according to the Oeconomy of the Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. But doubtleſs he makes a very ill uſe of this Maxim, which may hold with relation to the Acts that conſtitute the Three Perſons, and are proper to every one; for inſtance, the Act of Generation, which is proper to the Father excluſively of the Son and Holy Ghoſt; but this maxim does not hinder us from being firmly perſuaded, that it was the Son only who took upon him the form of a Servant in the ſingularity of his Perſon, and not in the Unity of the Divine Nature, in what was proper to the Son, and not in that which was common to the whole Trinity. This is diſtinctly expreſſed by the forged <hi>Dyoniſius de div. Nom. c.</hi> 2. &amp;c. and approved in the ſixth General Council, Act 8. where his Authority is made uſe of, and it is alſo acknowledged by <hi>Damaſc. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de fide c.</hi> 3. by <hi>Elias Cretenſis</hi> upon the fifth Oration of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and by <hi>Nicetas de fid. Orthod. c.</hi> 34. M. <hi>Hill</hi> ſhould have known beſides, that in the miſſion of the Perſons <hi>ad extra,</hi> the action by which they act upon a particular Subject is proper to them, and is common to the three Perſons only in reſpect to the Will; the acts of which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the three Perſons.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:62374:21"/>
            <p>You ſee, Sir, how the Biſhop has fallen into the hands of a Man, who underſtands things only by halves. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> is not pleaſed with the Biſhop's way of treating the Fathers, but he is yet more offended at the Explication and Notion which the Biſhop advances of the Doctrine of the Trinity: This is what the Biſhop ſays, <hi>p.</hi> 104. <q>We do plainly perceive in our ſelves two, if not three Principles of Operation, that do not only differ, as Underſtanding and Will, which are only different modes of Thinking, but dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in their Character and way of Operation. All our Cogitations and Reaſonings are a ſort of Acts, in which we can reflect on the way how we operate: We perceive that we Act freely in them, and that we turn our Minds to ſuch Objects and Thoughts as we pleaſe. But by another Principle, of which we perceive no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and can reflect upon no part of it, we live in our bodies, we animate and actuate them, we receive ſenſations from them, and give mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to them, we live and dye, and do not know how all this is done. It ſeems to be from ſome emanation from our Souls, in which we do not feel that we have any liberty, and ſo we muſt conclude, that this Principle in us is Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Neceſſary. In acts of Memory, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and Diſcourſe, there ſeems to be a mixture of both Principles, or a third that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults out of them. For we feel a freedom in one reſpect, but as for thoſe marks that are in our Brain, that ſet things in our Memory, or furniſh us with words, we are neceſſary Agents; they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62374:22"/> come in our way, but we do not know how: We cannot call up a figure of things or words at pleaſure; ſome diſorder in our Mechaniſm hides or flattens them, which when it goes off, they ſtart up and ſerve us, but not by any act of our Underſtanding and Will. Thus we ſee, that in this ſingle undivided Eſſence of ours, there are different Principles of Operation, ſo different as Liberty and Neceſſity are from one another. I am far from thinking that this is a proper Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation or Reſemblance of this Myſtery, yet it may be called, in ſome ſort, an Illuſtration of it; ſince it ſhews us from our own Compoſition, that in one Eſſence there may be ſuch different Principles, which in their proper Character may be brought to the terms of a contradiction, of being free and not free. So in the Divine Eſſence, which is the ſimpleſt and perfecteſt Unity, there may be three that may have a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Operations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> thinks that this Notion is not leſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to explain the Trinity, than that of the Fathers; Thus he ſpeaks, <hi>p.</hi> 106. <q>This is a worthy Simile indeed (to ſupplant that ſcouted one of the Ancients) in which is no repreſentation of the <hi>Logos,</hi> and its Parent Principle, nor of the Spirit of Holineſs that is in the Father and the Son, nor one of their Co-eſſentiality, Co-eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity or Order, all which are reſembled in that Simile which this undermines.</q> Then he Examins it particularly, and endeavours to ſhew many abſurdities in it. One may eaſily judge, that it is not hard for him to do this. If all the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62374:22"/> Similies given of the Trinity, ought to expreſs all that we conceive of it, what Simile can we uſe? At this rate, how can we juſtifie that reſemblance uſed by <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> of the Root and the Branches, to give us an Idea of the Co-equality? And that other, of a Fountain, a River, and a Vapour. That which makes Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> to be ſo unfair a Critick, is, that he does not conſider, that Similies are uſed generally for one particular deſign. When a Divine would expreſs the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiality, he brings Reſemblances that ſerve only for his purpoſe, and he does not matter whether they explain the whole <hi>Dogma</hi> of the Trinity, or not. The Biſhop therefore was in the right, to uſe a Simile, which ſerved to prove what he deſigned to eſtabliſh, namely, that in a moſt ſimple Subſtance there may be various Principles of Operations. A Man muſt have but little judgment, to think that he was bound to ſeek for ſome of another nature. It's very obſervable, that St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who has advanced more Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies than any of the Ancients, as you may ſee in his Books of the Trinity, from the ſixth to the fifteenth, which is the laſt, declares himſelf in the 15th Book, Chap. 7. that they are very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect and unlike, and that it's vain for us to ſeek in Created things, repreſentations of an incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible Myſtery. If the Biſhop has not made uſe of that Notion of the <hi>Logos,</hi> which ſignifies the Reaſon upon which <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Nazianze</hi> have inſiſted, it is becauſe he thinks that that Name is not ſo much given to the Second Perſon, becauſe he is the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the Father, as becauſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62374:23"/> (according to thoſe Divines who have more accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately Examin'd the Stile of Scripture.) St. <hi>John</hi> has reſpect in that word to the deſcription of the Creation, and to the Miniſtery of the Meſſias, by which God did always expreſs himſelf, according to the Hypotheſis of the Ancients. But what would Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſay, if by ill luck it appeared, that what the Biſhop has alledged to illuſtrate the Trinity, were the Notion of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelf in his Books of the Trinity? And yet this might be eaſily proved, if it were worth our while. I confeſs Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> will find in the Ninth Book, that there, for a reſemblance of the Trinity, he gives us Man Created after God's Image, in whom he finds a ſort of Trinity, namely, a Mind, a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelf, and a Love by which Man loves himſelf. But tho' this be Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s favourite Notion, and that of many Schoolmen, yet St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> in his Tenth Book prefers another before it, which ſeems clearer to him, and more proper to explain the Idea's of the Trinity, that is Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, Underſtanding, and Will. In fine, as if theſe Notions could not ſatisfie him, he borrows Similies from Brutes, Plants and Trees, from the inward Senſes, from Learning and Wiſdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And after all, he is forced to confeſs, that all theſe Repreſentations cannot give us a perfect Idea of the Trinity. If we had ſome portion of Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Criticiſing Spirit, here were a large field to ſhew many diſſimilitudes in thoſe Similies, but he who can give himſelf that trouble, muſt have little to do, and had need to have a very patient Reader to bear the tediouſneſs of it.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:62374:23"/>
            <p>We are come at laſt to Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Syſtem, which he oppoſes and prefers to that of the Biſhop, as having nothing in it, but what is drawn both from Scripture and Antiquity. And firſt, I muſt give him his due, and acknowledge that he ſays many good and Orthodox things upon this matter. I agree with him, when he tells us, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive three Minds in God, without eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing Treitheiſm, <hi>p.</hi> 112. But he is abſolutely miſtaken, when he denies, that ſeveral of the Ancients have acknowledged three Minds in God. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> may eaſily be convinced of this; he owns, <hi>p.</hi> 113. that to acknowledge three Minds in God, is by conſequence to acknowledge three Subſtances; but nothing is more evident, than that moſt of the Fathers have acknowledged three Subſtances. This would be ſoon demonſtrated; if I would inſiſt upon the Expreſſions of the Fathers, who have followed <hi>Plato</hi>'s Notions; for it's not the Father which the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> does, but it's the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Dr. <hi>Cudworth, p.</hi> 591. of his Syſtem, has given us the reaſon why the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> did ſo, by ſhewing, that they looked upon the Notion of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as inconſiſtent with the moſt ſimple Nature of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which they conceived as the ſource of the Deity, that was communicated to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This may be ſeen in <hi>Macrobius, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>in Somn. Soip. C.</hi> 14. From whence it appears, that the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Teniſon</hi> do agree, acknowledged three Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in their Trinity. Mr. <hi>Huet</hi> owns as much, in his <hi>Origeniana,</hi> concerning thoſe Divines who
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62374:24"/> did, like <hi>Origen,</hi> follow the Notions of <hi>Plato,</hi> to explain the Doctrine of the Trinity.</p>
            <p>But we have yet more evident proofs of this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> truth. 1. It is certain that the <hi>Greeks,</hi> before the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> have conſtantly ſuppoſed that there were three Hypoſtaſes in the <hi>Trinity;</hi> and it's no leſs certain, than that by three Hypoſtaſes the <hi>Greeks</hi> underſtood three Subſtances. The thing is ſo unqueſtionable, that the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> uſes the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for one and the ſame thing. I know that St. <hi>Baſil</hi> in his 78 Epiſtle, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to give another ſenſe to theſe words of the Council, but we may juſtly oppoſe to him <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> who had been at the Council of <hi>Nice:</hi> For he expreſly affirms in his fifth Oration againſt the <hi>Arians,</hi> that the Father and the Son have but one Nature and Hypoſtaſis; he ſays the ſame in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Liberius,</hi> and in that to the Biſhops of <hi>Africk,</hi> where he poſitively aſſerts that the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis is the Nature. We may further oppoſe to St. <hi>Baſil, Alexander</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who had been as it were the ſoul of the Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> for in his Letters, the one mentioned by <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and the other by <hi>Socrates,</hi> he takes conſtantly Hypoſtaſis for Eſſence. This we ſee likewiſe in the addition to the Synodical Epiſtle of the Fathers of <hi>Sardica</hi> in <hi>Theodoret, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>C.</hi> 6. where they charge the <hi>Arians</hi> with believing three Hypoſtaſis, becauſe they believed three different Subſtances, that of the Father, that of the Son, and that of the Holy Ghoſt. The ſame may alſo be obſerved in the 57. Epiſtle of St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> which he writes to Pope <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus,</hi> where he maintains, that to ſay three Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſes,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62374:24"/> is the ſame as to ſay three Subſtances, and that all men ſpeak ſo, when they will ſpeak <hi>Greek.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That too many of the <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers, who have diſputed againſt the <hi>Sabellians,</hi> have taken theſe words in this ſenſe, is but too evident from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> Sirnamed the Great. This great Man is vindicated by <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> as having never entertained any impious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion about the <hi>Trinity.</hi> But St. <hi>Baſil</hi> rejects him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many Articles, chiefly where he confirms the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie; if he defends him ſomewhere, it's only with this Apology, that while he too eagerly intends to confute the <hi>Sabellians,</hi> he falls into the contrary opinion; and beſides, he accuſes him of having impious Opinions concerning the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Phot. Cod.</hi> 232. <hi>pag.</hi> 902. I have obſerved this concerning <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> 1. Becauſe the <hi>Arians</hi> boaſted that he was of their ſide. 2. Becauſe <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> follows ſome of his Expreſſions, in his Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodical Epiſtle to all the Biſhops, when he accuſes <hi>Arius</hi> of not believing the Son to be like the Father in reſpect of his Nature, and calls the Father and the Son <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, juſt as <hi>Origen</hi> had done. 3. Becauſe Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> has ſuffered himſelf to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon by a ſpurious piece, which he cites under the name of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> as truly his, but it's viſibly falſe, ſince the Doctrine it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains is altogether contrary to what we know to have been the Doctrine of that Ancient Author.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. It's certain that moſt of the Ancient Fathers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> before the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> have held a Generation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62374:25"/> of the <hi>Word in tempore,</hi> before the Creation of the World<note n="*" place="margin">Juſtin. M. Ap. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>66.</hi> E. Dial. cum Tryph. p. <hi>285.</hi> D. <hi>358.</hi> B.C. <hi>359.</hi> B. Athenag. Legat. pro Chriſtianis, p. <hi>10.</hi> D. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phil. ad Autol. p. <hi>88.</hi> B. p. <hi>100.</hi> B. Tatian p. <hi>145.</hi> B. Clem. Alex. Strom. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>553.</hi> B. <hi>591.</hi> B. Strom. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>644.</hi> A. Strom. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>700.</hi> c. Tertull. Apol. c. <hi>21.</hi> p. <hi>19.</hi> contra Herm. c. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>18. 20. 45.</hi> adv. Prax. c. <hi>5. 7. 12.</hi> Lact. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>177, 178.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>364, 365. 366.</hi>
               </note>. The Learned Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> has given us a long Liſt of them, and Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> owns it, calling this a <hi>ſingularly odd notion.</hi> It was the great Argument of the <hi>Arians,</hi> who concluded from thence that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had aſſerted that Jeſus Chriſt was of another Subſtance with the Father, as being made and created, which they proved by thoſe paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Fathers, where they uſe the words <hi>made</hi> and <hi>created.</hi> Now its certain, that <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> does not ſerve himſelf of the Notion of this Generation <hi>in tempore</hi> before the Creation, to oppoſe the <hi>Arians,</hi> but urges on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Generation of the Son by the Father <hi>ab aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> to prove that Jeſus Chriſt was not made before the World, and that he was Creator and not a Creature. In this ſenſe we ought to take the words of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, which may juſtly be looked upon as the confirmation of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodical Letter to all the Biſhops. This Remark is the more neceſſary, becauſe moſt of thoſe who have diſputed againſt the <hi>Arians</hi> after the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> have abandoned the Syſtem of the Ancients, concerning the two Productions of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Alexander</hi> had abandon'd it: This great man being it ſeems more uſed to this Controverſie, had found that this ſecond production gave mighty advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the <hi>Arians.</hi> If the Reader have a mind to know what thoſe advantages were, we may eaſily ſatisfie him. 1. The Fathers following ſome Texts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62374:25"/> of Scripture, granted that the ſecond Nativity of the Son, would make him to be look'd upon as Created; it was in oppoſition to this that the Council defined, <hi>genitum, &amp; non factum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It gave occaſion to believe that the Son was not eternal, and that the Father had not been Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ab aeterno,</hi> which did abſolutely deſtroy the Divinity of the Son.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is to be obſerved, that <hi>Origen</hi> as well as <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> having been cited by the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> as their great Author, to prove that the Son was begotten and made <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it was afterward defined, that the Son was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in reſpect of the Eſſence, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe he was not made; this is <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>'s Obſervation againſt the <hi>Origeniſts, Parag.</hi> 8. where he accuſes <hi>Origen</hi> to have called the Son of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Deum factum.</hi> See <hi>Valeſ. ad Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is evident, that tho ſome believe that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which was uſed in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> denotes the Numerical Unity of the Divine Eſſence: Yet many of the Fathers have uſed it only to expreſs the ſame Specifical Eſſence. Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> has very well obſerved it, <hi>Pag.</hi> 611. upon a paſſage of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> and another or <hi>Athanaſius. Athanaſius</hi> ſpeaks thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Expoſit. fid. p.</hi> 241. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> makes the ſame remark, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>H.</hi> 76. <hi>n.</hi> 17. from whence Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> draws this Concluſion: <q>It's plain, that the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62374:26"/> Orthodox Fathers aſſerted no ſuch thing, as one and the ſame ſingular or numerical Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; of the ſeveral Perſons of the Trinity, this according to them being not a real Trinity, but a Trinity of meer Names, Notions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adequate Conceptions only.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. You ought to know, that the Fathers for the moſt part, have a Notion very frequent in their Writings, till St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s Time, who did confute it, and obliged thoſe by whom it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, to reject it; which is, that the Father alone being of his own Nature inviſible, the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions of God mentioned in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not be aſcribed to him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Add</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus l. <hi>2.</hi> ad Autoly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, p. <hi>100.</hi> Tertul. adv. Jud. c. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>194.</hi> adv. Marcion. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>27.</hi> p. <hi>395, 396.</hi> Synodus Antiochena Concil. To. <hi>1.</hi> Ed. Lab. To. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>845</hi> D. Euſeb. Hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> but that they muſt be referred only to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as to him whom the Father has not only employed as a Miniſter in the Creation, but by whom alſo he always Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed himſelf under the Old Teſtament. This may be ſeen in <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> Dial. againſt <hi>Tryph. p.</hi> 275. <hi>A.</hi> 283. <hi>B.</hi> and 357. <hi>B. C.</hi> in <hi>Tertullian</hi> againſt <hi>Praxeas, p.</hi> 648. in <hi>Novatian. lib. de Trinit.</hi> Now this Notion, ſuppoſed that the Father and the Son were not of the ſame Nature; and without doubt, this was the reaſon why St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> did reject and confute it, as appears in his Books of the Trinity.</p>
            <p>It were endleſs, to take notice of all thoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the Fathers, which import a diverſity of Subſtance; it's enough to have conſidered the moſt remarkable, out of the chief Authors, cited by Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> to confirm his Syſtem, ſuch as <hi>Origen,</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> Sirnamed the Great, who is eſpecially famous for having oppoſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellianiſm,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62374:26"/> to which I could add ſome paſſages out of <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> reported by <hi>Photius, Cod.</hi> 106. and out of <hi>Theognoſtus</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Photius, Cod.</hi> 106. I ſhall not take notice of thoſe which relate to the Holy Ghoſt, of whom they ſpeak meaner yet than of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> may read what <hi>Theognoſtus</hi> ſays of him in <hi>Photius, Cod.</hi> 106. and <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his Inſtitutions, and <hi>Euſebius</hi> againſt <hi>Marcellus</hi> of <hi>Ancyra;</hi> after this, let him ſay, if he dare, that the Fathers have conſtantly acknowledged but one Subſtance of the three Perſons; and if they have not acknowledged this, with what Confidence did he impute to them an Opinion, which how true ſoever, is yet quite contrary to their Doctrine?</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing which may be Cenſured in Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Hypotheſis concerning the Trinity, is, that it accommodates the Scripture to the Syſtem of <hi>Thomas Aquinas.</hi> I have obſerved before, that the Scripture ſpeaks of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, under another Notion, than that of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which contains and judges of the Idea's that are in the mind. <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philact</hi> is aware of this, upon the 1ſt of St. <hi>John,</hi> where he rejects that famous diviſion of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in diſputing againſt Porphiry; and all the more Learned Divines do likewiſe acknowledge it; whereas <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> to give a Reaſon why there are but three Perſons in the Trinity, builds upon the two Faculties, of Underſtanding and Will, which we conceive in the Humane Soul. I confeſs, that St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> may have given ſome occaſion to the Schoolmen to frame that Syſtem, and to apply it to the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62374:27"/> Words of Scripture, which ſpeak of the Trinity. But upon this, I have three things to obſerve againſt Mr. <hi>Hill.</hi> 1. That tho' the Doctrine of the Trinity is clearly explained in Scripture, as to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; yet there are ſuch difficulties about the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that it were by much the wiſeſt thing to ſpeak of it only in Scripture words. This was the Maxim of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in his Letter to <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Byzantium;</hi> where he ſays, that <hi>St. John</hi> has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed the generation of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe it is incomprehenſible to Men and Angels, and that one cannot without Impiety dive into this Myſtery. <hi>Ireneus</hi> hath a whole Chapter to prove <hi>Generatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ejus inenarrabilem eſſe,</hi> in which he ſpeaks to the Hereticks in words as put againſt the Schoolmen, <hi>vos autem Generationem ejus ex Patre divinantes, &amp; verbi hominum per linguam factam prolationem transfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes in verbum Dei juſte delegimini a nobis. Et addimus ſi quis itaque nobis dixerit, quomodo ergo filius prolatus a Patre eſſe, dicimus ei quia prolationem iſtam ſive Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerationem, ſive nuncupationem, ſive adapertionem, aut quomodolibet, quis nomine vocaverit Generationem ejus inenarrabilem exiſtentem, nemo novit niſi ſolus qui generavit, Pater, &amp; qui natus eſt Filius,</hi> &amp;c. This was alſo the Maxim of St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> in his ſecond Book againſt <hi>Eunomius, p.</hi> 44. where he affirms, that we ought not to aſcribe any thing to the Son, but what is expreſly attributed to him in Scripture; and that we ought not to ſpeak of God, but in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Terms, this is repeated in his Book <hi>de vera fide, p.</hi> 250. It was alſo the Notion of <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Nazianze, Orat.</hi> 12. <hi>p.</hi> 204. Where he ſays, that the Trinity alone comprehends, <hi>quo ordine erga ſe ſit.</hi> In his thirteenth Oration, <hi>p.</hi> 211. and in 23. he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62374:27"/> declares, that if he were asked the <hi>Modus</hi> of the Eternal Generation and Proceſſion, he would leave it to them who alone know themſelves, according to the Teſtimony of Scripture. <hi>In divinis ſcientia ſuae ignorantiae maxima ſcientia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is, that ſince the Fathers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that the Myſtery of the Trinity is unknown to us, and even to the Angelical Beings, it were very prudently done, never to engage our ſelves into thoſe Explanations, much leſs to deliver them with an Authority almoſt equal to that of Scripture. This is the Judgment of St. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> Sirnamed the Divine, in his 12th <hi>Orat.</hi> For after all, to what purpoſe are all thoſe Similies uſed in this caſe? Since the ſame <hi>Gregory</hi> owns, that after having ſearched curiouſly for ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the Trinity, he could never meet with any, that was able to ſatisfie him; ſo that he frankly declares, that that of the Eye, that of a Fountain and a River, that of the Sun, the Beams and the Light, or any other whatſoever, were not proper Images of the Myſtery of the Trinity. <hi>Orat.</hi> 37. <hi>p.</hi> 611.</p>
            <p>The third thing which may be blamed in Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Hypotheſis, wherein he has blended the Notions of the <hi>Thomiſts</hi> with thoſe of Scripture, is that it is not liked even by a great part of thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> For the <hi>Scotiſts</hi> make great Exceptions againſt it, and the difficulties which they urge againſt the <hi>Thomiſts,</hi> ſerve at beſt to render this matter more obſcure and intricate. All their working to prove that there cannot be more than three Perſons in the Divine Eſſence, ſeems to me as ſolid, as what <hi>Ireneus</hi> ſays, that there could
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62374:28"/> not have been more than four Goſpels, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Grotius</hi> does ſome-where very much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the way of the Patriarch <hi>Gennadius,</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> in his Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith, which he preſented to the Emperor <hi>Mahomet</hi> II. And indeed it is very commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and it were to be wiſhed that thoſe many Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines who are ſo poſitive, would imitate the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty of it, in explaining thoſe great Truths which the Scripture propoſes to us, that we may receive them with ſubmiſſion of Faith, and not pry into them, and give Syſtems of 'em, in which upon examination it appears, that Humane Reaſon has a greater ſhare than Divine Revelation.</p>
            <p>It is not my deſign at preſent to examine more particularly Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Hypotheſis concerning the <hi>Trinity:</hi> A Learned Reader can eaſily ſee that he has compiled Dr. <hi>Bull.</hi> But it were to be wiſhed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he had quoted the Fathers with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more judgment, and cited only thoſe that made for him; for that way of quoting Authors in a lump, is eaſie enough, and may impoſe upon thoſe who never converſed with Antiquity; but it does very little honour to a Writer among thoſe who are true Judges: I am ſure, that if a man who is not a Scholar, would compare Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Citations, with what he reads in <hi>Engliſh</hi> of the Doctrine of thoſe Fathers, in the Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Bibliotheque</hi> of Mr. <hi>Dupin,</hi> a Doctor of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> he would be ſtrangely ſurprized to ſee that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> cites for his Opinion a great number of Authors who are Diametrically oppoſite to him. But if Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> was to undergo the Cenſure of the Learned, who
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62374:28"/> have ſtudied theſe matters in the Originals, he has laid himſelf open to a very heavy one.</p>
            <p>The 2d. thing to be wiſhed, is that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> had not inſpired his Readers with ſo profound a Veneration for Antiquity: It ſeems he has had the ordinary fate of thoſe who diſpute with too much heat; thinking that the Biſhop rejected Antiquity with too great a contempt, he ſeems on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to acknowledge the Authority of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents as a Tradition almoſt infallible. If he is read in Antiquity, as he would fain perſwade us he is, then he muſt be given over as a man paſt Cure, ſince his own reading could not bring him to have true and right notions concerning the Authority of the Ancients; but if he never read the Fathers, but relies upon the Extracts of others, I deſire him to be a little better acquainted with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Doctors, before he preſume to impoſe upon his Readers that blind Veneration for Antiquity, which he preſcribes to them. Tho moſt of the Fathers from the middle of the ſecond Century to the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> had been engaged in Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions contrary to the right notion we have of the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> as <hi>Petavius</hi> confeſſes it; this would make no impreſſion upon me, ſince thoſe Fathers did acknowledge the Authority of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, from whence I may immediately derive the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity;</hi> I ſay this would not make me doubt of the revealed Doctrine. Nay, more than that, I ſay that tho the whole Council of <hi>Nice</hi> had followed the opinion of thoſe Fathers, it would not much move me; they were men, and liable to be miſtaken, and thoſe who can deny this
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62374:29"/> truth had as good renounce their Reformation all at once. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> muſt remember what St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith upon this very Queſtion, in his Apology againſt <hi>Rufinus: Et quomodo, (ô</hi> Rufine) <hi>inquies, in libris eccleſiaſticorum ſcriptorum vitia nonnulla ſunt? Si Cauſas vitiorum neſcire reſpondero, non ſtatim illos haereticos indicabo; fieri enim poteſt ut vel ſimpliciter erraverint, vel alio ſenſu ſcripſerint, vel a librariis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritis eorum paulatim ſcripta corrupta ſint, vel certè, antequam in Alexandria quaſi Daemonium Meridianum Arius naſceretur, innocentes quaedam &amp; minus cautè locuti ſint, &amp; quae non poſſint perverſorum hominum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniam declinare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is what I had to ſay upon the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Fathers undertaken by Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> and upon the Syſtem which he oppoſes to the falſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he aſcribes to the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury.</hi> You ſee that the Fathers had need of another Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt, eſpecially, ſince by the way he was pleaſed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To give a wipe to <hi>Tertullian,</hi> the firſt in his opinion who defended the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> againſt <hi>Praxeas;</hi> he ſays that his words and his ſenſe are ſometimes very ſingularly odd concerning the Production of the Second Perſon: And yet it's very obſervable, that <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſays nothing, but what has been advanced by many other Eccleſiaſtical Writers before the Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> ſo that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Endeavours to reduce what theſe Fathers ſay to an Orthodox ſenſe, <hi>Mr. Hill</hi> muſt of neceſſity involve them in the ſame cenſure with <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2ly. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> affirms concerning the Fathers, that in his opinion they generally taught a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62374:29"/> Adoption, and a Metaphorical <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of our Nature in Jeſus Chriſt, and of all the Saints by him. But to juſtifie them in this Particular, we muſt ſay either, that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> never read them, or that if he did, he quarrels with them with as little ground, as when he cenſures the Biſhop for uſing the Expreſſion of Divine Perſon in ſpeaking of the Fleſh; for both the Biſhop and the Fathers, who often call Jeſus Chriſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, have had the ſame Idea, ſo that they muſt either ſtand or fall together. But I ſhall take leave of this unfair Writer, when I have performed one thing that I promiſed.</p>
            <p>I told you that I was very much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to find in Mr. <hi>Hills</hi> Book a moſt dangerous Principle; I muſt now make you ſenſible of it.</p>
            <p>Theſe are his words, <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. <q>What I require, is, that the Catholick Doctrine be aſſerted as a Rule of Faith, which the Church is bound to adhere to on the certain Authority of Divine Revelation; this Revelation appearing real, not only to particular mens private Opinions, but originally committed to the charge and cuſtody of the whole Church by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; and ſo preſerved by their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62374:30"/> throughout the whole diffuſive body: Whereas his Lordſhip only lays down this notion or form of Faith: That we believe Points of Doctrine, becauſe we are perſwaded that they are revealed to us in Scripture; which is ſo languid and unſafe a Rule, that it will reſolve Faith into every man's private Fancies and Contradictory Opinions: Since each man's Faith is his Perſwaſion, that what he believes for a Doctrine is revealed in Scripture. Whereas the act of a Chriſtian Faith believes ſuch Doctrine to be true and fundamental in Chriſtianity from the certain evidence thereof in the Scriptures, acknowledged by all Churches not led by caſual perſwaſions, but by a Primitive, perpetual, univerſal and unanimous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and Tradition. The deviation from which Rule and Notion, to private Opinions and Perſwaſions, is the cauſe of all Hereſies, and, by its conſequent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, naturally tends to the ruine of the True Chriſtian and Catholick Faith.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> is angry with the Biſhop, for ſaying that we believe Points of Doctrine, becauſe we are perſwaded that they are revealed in Scripture; he thinks the Biſhop ſhould have ſaid, that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Doctrine for fundamental, from
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62374:30"/> the evidence thereof in the Scriptures, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all Churches, not led by caſual perſwaſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe Expreſſions are ſo intricate, that it's hard to gueſs at Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s meaning. If theſe words, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all Churches, relate to the word <hi>Scripture,</hi> which goes immediately before, it's very hard to apply what he ſays to all the Books of Scripture, ſo as that they may retain their Authority with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; for it is notorious, that divers Books of Scripture, as the Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> &amp;c. have not that Primitive, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, and unanimous Tradition to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their Authority. This one Clauſe of Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s will deprive us, at one daſh, of all the Books, the Authority whereof we are told, in <hi>Euſebius</hi>'s Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, was for a long time queſtioned by great Churches. But if he refers the words, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all Churches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Fundamental Doctrines, as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his Diſcourſe, the Maxim of <hi>Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Lyrinenſis,</hi> which he cites, and what he ſays concerning the Creeds, ſeem to intimate, then this Propoſition is not leſs dangerous than the other.</p>
            <p>It is true, that a Fundamental Doctrine, the Revelation whereof is acknowledged by all the Churches, is moſt evident by that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62374:31"/> very thing, that all the World does ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it. But muſt therefore all the Fundamental Doctrines, which have not been acknowledged by all the Churches, tho they are clearly revealed in Scripture, be thought not fundamental, becauſe they want this Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence?</p>
            <p>I confeſs Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſays, that he will not examine what Rules private men are to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; but he affirms, that thoſe who deſire to arrive at a ripeneſs of Judgment and Knowledge, ought to take the Rule of <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius Lyrinenſis,</hi> p. 7. which the Biſhop has rejected.</p>
            <p>But this, I ſay firſt of all, is a Notion that has no ſolid ground in Divinity: 'Tis grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that Certainty of Revelation, in reſpect to thoſe who live now, I depends upon the Certainty of Revelation which the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical, and after it the Chriſtian Church, has had down to this time. But it is not a wild imagination, to oppoſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Certainty which the Apoſtolical Church in a Body has bad, to the perſwaſion of each Member of the Apoſtolical Church? What Certainty could the Body of the Apoſtolical Church have, but the Certainty which each ſingle member of which it was compoſed had? Who ever heard, among Proteſtants, but
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62374:31"/> that the Faith of each private man reſolves it ſelf into the Certainty of Revelation, which way ſoever he may come by that Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Revelation?</p>
            <p>Is it not rank Popery to aſſert, that our Faith is not immediately reſolved into the Authority of God, who propoſes a Doctrine to us in Scripture? Pray where ſhall we find Chriſtians, if to be ſo, it is not enough to believe a Doctrine becauſe Chriſt has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it; but one muſt believe beſides, ſuch a Doctrine to be true and fundamental in Chriſtianity, from its certain evidence in Scripture, acknowledged by all Churches not led by caſual perſwaſions, but by a Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, perpetual, univerſal and unanimous Conviction and Tradition?</p>
            <p>One might perhaps think at firſt, that this addition to the definition of Faith were no great matter; but I aſſure you, Sir, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys entirely the nature of Faith, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the whole Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> upon this Point; it imports that the Goſpel has no Authority, <hi>quo ad nos,</hi> till it is vouched by the Authority of the Church. The Church has been believed hitherto to be the Depoſitary of Scripture. But it was never believed that her Authority went ſo far, as that we ought not to receive a truth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62374:32"/> evident in Revelation, but as it is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all the Churches not led by caſual perſwaſions, but by a Primitive, perpetual, univerſal and unanimous Conviction and Tradition.</p>
            <p>Indeed, Sir, if what Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> lays down be true, it's hard to tell who has Faith now? I deſire Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> to reflect upon that Article of the Creed, which eſtabliſhes the Proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>ab utroque,</hi> and to tell me whether he does not think himſelf bound to believe it, till he has examined whether this is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all the Churches not led by caſual perſwaſions, but by a Primitive, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, univerſal and unanimous Conviction and Tradition? It is ſomewhat ſtrange, to ſee a Proteſtant uſe that as a neceſſary Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter to eſtabliſh Faith, which the Papiſts employ to deſtroy it? The Papiſt thinks to have driven the Proteſtant to the impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of ſhewing how Faith is produced in a man who reads the Scripture, becauſe ſuch a man can't be ſure whether his being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded by Revelation of ſome Fundamental Truth, is a ground he may ſafely rely upon, before he has Examined whether all the Churches agree upon that point, that ſeems to be Revealed, or not. And Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> it ſeems, being not ſatisfied with what we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this Objection, thinks fit to ſide
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62374:32"/> with the Papiſt. How edifying this proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can be, let Divines judge.</p>
            <p>Pray, Sir, tell me what you think of this, when you hear it ſaid, that Faith has been ſo intruſted to the Cuſtody of the whole Church by the Apoſtles, that it was preſerved by the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles? <q>But what I require, ſays Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> is, that the Catholick Doctrine be aſſerted as a Rule of Faith, which the Church is bound to adhere to, on the certain Authority of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation; this Revelation appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing real, not only to particular Mens private Opinions, but originally commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the charge and cuſtody of the whole Church by the Apoſtles, and ſo preſerved by their Succeſſors, throughout the whole diffuſive body, <hi>p.</hi> 6.</q> Does Faith then depend upon the knowledge of the Apoſtles Succeſſors, or their faithfulneſs or unfaithfulneſs in keeping this Sacred Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum? This puts me in mind of what <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez</hi> ſays, that the Faith of a Chriſtian does ſo abſolutely depend upon the Authority of his Leaders, that if at this day a Heathen being caſt by a ſtorm into <hi>England,</hi> did em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Belief of our Church, which rejects Tranſubſtantiation, he would be in a ſtate of Salvation; tho' the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which alledges Tradition for this <hi>Dogma,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:62374:33"/> and has it in her Creed, declares that one can't be Saved without profeſſing that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Doctrine.</p>
            <p>I know St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> has ſaid, <hi>non crede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Evangelio niſi me moveret Eccleſiae Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas;</hi> it ſeems Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> was deceived by this Maxim, which the Papiſts have adopted after they had corrupted it: For St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks only of the Miniſtery of the Church, in propoſing the Goſpels as written by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Divinely Inſpired. This was well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by <hi>Melchior Canus, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. The ſame Miniſtry may be attributed to the Church, with relation to the Creeds that it propoſes to us, as a faithful Abridgment of the Apoſtles Doctrine; but it is ridiculous to imagine, that we cannot produce an Act of Chriſtian Faith, without knowing the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral conſent of all the Churches in profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſame Truths. It is not the conſent of the Church, that makes a Doctrine either true or fundamental, the Nature of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine it ſelf makes it ſo. A Divine, who has pored long upon Antiquity, may by an exact ſtudy and meditation, have informed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of that conſent; but this ſerves more for his particular Inſtruction, and for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of his own Theological Notions, concerning the diſtinction of Points funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, from Points that are not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62374:33"/> than to confirm his Faith as he is a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> makes a ſtrange uſe of the Maxim of <hi>Vincentius Lyrinenſis, quod ubique, quod ſemper, quod ab omnibus,</hi> &amp;c. That Prieſt was a <hi>Semipelagian,</hi> that is, he thought that a Man could believe by his own ſtrength, and that afterward God gave him Grace to Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his Good and Pious Reſolutions. He introduced this Maxim merely in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who pretended to have found his Doctrine concerning Grace in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles; ſo that this Father was obliged, either to confute the Fathers, or to abandon his Doctrine, which he had cauſed to be Authoriſed by the Councils of <hi>Africa.</hi> After all, he confeſſes himſelf, that his Method could only be of uſe againſt new-born Hereſies, ſuch as he pretended St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s Doctrine to be. There is nothing more eaſie, ſays Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> than for us to be informed of the Belief of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. I confeſs, we have their Symbols and Summaries of Faith, but Symbols have
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62374:34"/> no Authority, but as they are extracted from Scripture; this our Articles expreſly tell us. And the Apoſtles Creed, as we call it, was never known in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> till within theſe few Centuries. What I have before mentioned upon the Article of the Proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>ab utroque,</hi> ſhews that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> has confounded what belongs to a Chriſtian, with what belongs only to Divines.</p>
            <p>However, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> grants, that Faith cannot be produced in a Man's Heart, but as far as he himſelf is perſuaded of the Truth of what he believes: But what he adds is extream raſh, when he aſſures us, that he, who cannot be perſuaded to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the common and eſtabliſhed Syſtems of the Faith of the Univerſal Church, upon the Authority of which, it always ſtood and ſtands to this day, or frames funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Principles upon his own private Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, does not belong to the Communion of Chriſt's Church, tho' he fancies his Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be Revealed in Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:62374:34"/>
            <p>I grant what Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> lays down, as to thoſe who advance fundamental Articles upon their private Opinion; he ſeems there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to reject the Articles which the Papiſts have introduced into the Creed, framed by <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth; but he can aſcribe no other Authority to Confeſſions of Faith or Symbols, but that which they borrow from their Conformity with Revelation the ſumm of which they contain. What he affirms, that the Catholick Church has always ſtood upon the Authority of Symbols, is a meer Viſion; the Church indeed made an Abſtract of Faith, for the uſe of <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenes,</hi> which we call the <hi>Creed;</hi> ſhe taught it to thoſe <hi>Cathecumenes,</hi> as an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment of what's Revealed; the Faith therefore of <hi>Cathecumenes,</hi> has an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate reſpect to Revelation; it muſt rely and be founded upon that, if it be true. In a word, Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> either becauſe he does not underſtand the matter, or out of a deſire to cenſure and contradict the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, explains his Opinion after a very odd manner, his Expreſſions do very much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62374:35"/> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and are far from being ſo exact as a Cenſor ought to be; he ſhews that he himſelf ſtands in need of a great deal of Indulgence and Chriſtian forbearance.</p>
            <p>I wiſh from my Heart he may come to himſelf, conſider his fault, and repent. If he could but for a minute reflect in cool blood, upon his outragious way of writing, and upon the Service that he has done to the Enemies of the Trinity, by endeavouring to ſacrifice to them one of the Defenders of it, for whoſe Talents he cannot but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſome eſteem, how averſe ſoever he may be to his Perſon, I am ſure he would be aſhamed of his Book. For notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his Paſſion, I am willing to believe, that the Chriſtian Spirit is not altogether extinguiſhed in him. I would have him conſider, that in the ſight of God, 'tis not he that receives, but he that does the Injury, that is Unhappy.</p>
            <p>If I have chanced in this Paper, to ſay
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62374:35"/> any thing that ſeems too ſevere againſt him, and that approaches too near to his Angry Strain, I humbly deſire, that without more ado, you would ſtrike it out, as being writ againſt my intention. I would by no means be my ſelf guilty of a fault, which I ſincerely lament when I find it in others, and which would but cover me with the more confuſion, if I ſhould be found to practiſe that which I condemn in another.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 12. 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>I am, Sir, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:62374:36"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</head>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Paſtoral Care. By the Right Reverend <hi>GIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Four Diſcourſes delivered to the Clergy of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſs of <hi>Sarum:</hi> Concerning, I. The Truth of the Chriſtian Religion. II. The Divinity and Death of Chriſt. III. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility and Authority of the Church. IV. The Obligations to continue in the Communion of the Church. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Memoirs of the moſt Reverend <hi>THOMAS CRANMER,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury:</hi> Wherein the Hiſtory of the Church, and the Reformation of it, during the Primacy of the ſaid Archbiſhop, are greatly illuſtrated, and many ſingular Matters relating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, now firſt publiſhed. In Three Books. Collected chiefly from Records, Regiſters, Authentick Letters, and other Original Manuſcripts. By <hi>John Strype,</hi> M. A. <hi>Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origo Leguin:</hi> Or, A Treatiſe of the Origine of Laws, and their Obliging Power; as alſo of their great Variety; and why ſome Laws are immutable, and ſome not, but may ſuffer change, or ceaſe to be, or be ſuſpended, or abrogated. In Seven Books. By <hi>George Dawſon. Fol.</hi> 1694.</p>
            <p>A brief Diſcourſe concerning the Lawfulneſs of Worſhipping God by the Common-Prayer; in Anſwer to a Book, intituled, <hi>[A Brief Diſcourſe of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs of Common-Prayer-Worſhip.]</hi> By <hi>John Williams,</hi> D. D. 4<hi>to.</hi> 1694.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>John Conaut</hi>'s Sermons, Publiſh'd by Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> 1693. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ruſhworth</hi>'s Hiſtorical Collections. The Third Part, in Two Volumes. Containing the Principal Matters which happened from the meeting of the Parliament, <hi>Nov.</hi> 3. 1640. to the end of the Year 1644. Wherein is a particular Account of the Riſe and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Civil War, to that Period. <hi>Fol.</hi> 1692.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the Troubles and Tryal of the Moſt Reverend Father in God <hi>WILLIAM LA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>D,</hi> Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury;</hi> Wrote by himſelf, during his Impriſonment in the <hi>Tower.</hi> To which is prefixed the Diary of his own Life, faithfully and entirely publiſhed from the Original Copy. And ſubjoyned a Supplement to the preceding Hiſtory; the Arch-Biſhop's Laſt Will: His Large Anſwer to the Lord <hi>Say</hi>'s Speech concerning Liturgies: His Annual Accounts of his Province deliver'd to the
<pb facs="tcp:62374:36"/> King, and ſome other Things relaying to the Hiſtory. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ubſiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by <hi>Henry Wharton,</hi> Chaplain to Archbiſhop <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt.</hi> And by his Grace's Command. <hi>Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Commentary on the Firſt Book of <hi>Moſes,</hi> called <hi>Geneſis.</hi> By the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Simon</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ely.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>The Hearts-Eaſe; or, a Remedy againſt all Troubles: With a Conſolatory Diſcourſe, particularly directed to thoſe who have loſt their Friends and Relations. To which is added two Papers, printed in the time of the late Plague. <hi>By</hi> the ſame Author 12 <hi>mo. (Reprinted.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe Of the Government of the Thoughts. By <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eo. Tully,</hi> Sub-Dean of <hi>York.</hi> The Second Edition. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Sarum's</hi> Sermon at the Funeral of Archbiſhop <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> Who dyed at <hi>Lambeth, Nov.</hi> 20. 1694.</p>
            <p>A Sermon concerning Holy Reſolution, Preached before the King at <hi>Kenſington: Decemb.</hi> 30. 1694. By his Grace Dr. <hi>Thomas Teniſon,</hi> Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Sermon at the Funeral of the Queen, in the <hi>Abby-Church</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter: March</hi> 5. 1694/5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hiſtoria de Epiſcopis &amp; Decanis Londinenſibus necnon de Epiſcopis &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canis Aſſavenſibus à prima Sedis utriuſque fundatione ad Annum</hi> MDXL. <hi>Acceſſit. Appendiae inſtrumentorum quorundam inſignium duplex. Autore</hi> Henrico Whartono, <hi>A. M.</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Poſſibility and Expediency and Neceſſity of Divine Revelation.</hi> A Sermon preach'd at St. <hi>Martin</hi>'s <hi>in the Fields,</hi> January 7. 1694/5. at the beginning of the Lecture for the enſuing Year, Founded by the Honourable <hi>Rob. Boyle</hi> Eſq; by <hi>John Williams,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>—<hi>The Certainty of Divine Revelation,</hi> being his Second Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preach'd at the ſaid Lecture, <hi>Feb.</hi> 4. 1695.</p>
            <p>—His Vindication of the Sermons of his Grace <hi>John</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> concerning the <hi>Divinity and Incarnation of our Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> and of the <hi>Lord Biſhop of Worceſter</hi>'s Sermon on the <hi>Myſteries of the Chriſtian Faith,</hi> from the Exceptions of a late <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian Book,</hi> Intituled, <hi>[Conſiderations on the Explications of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Trinity.]</hi> To which is annexed a Letter from the <hi>Lord Biſhop of Sarum,</hi> to the Author of the ſaid <hi>Vindication,</hi> on the ſame Subject. 1695. 4<hi>to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay on the Memory of the late QUEEN. By <hi>Gilbert</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sarum:</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remarks of an Univerſity Man upon a late Book, falſly called, [<hi>A Vindication of the Primitive Fathers, againſt the Imputations of</hi> Gilbert <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Sarum, <hi>Written by Mr.</hi> Hill <hi>of</hi> Kilmington.] 4<hi>to.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Characters of Divine Revelation.</hi> A Sermon Preached at St. <hi>Martin's in the Fields, March</hi> 4. 1694/5. Being the Third of
<pb facs="tcp:62374:37"/> the Lecture for the enſuing Year, founded by the Honourable <hi>Robert Boyle,</hi> Eſquire. By <hi>John Williams,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Of Sincerity and conſtancy in the Faith and Profeſſion of the True Religion, in ſeveral Sermons. By the moſt Reverend Dr. <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> late Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Publiſhed from the Originals, by <hi>Ralph Barker.</hi> D. D. Chaplain to his Grace. 8<hi>vo.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THere will be publiſhed ſeveral other Sermons and Diſcourſes of the moſt Reverend Dr. <hi>JOHN TILLOTSON,</hi> late Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> by order of his Adminiſtratrix, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſcribed from his own Papers, by Dr. <hi>Ralph Barker</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to his Grace. Which are diſpoſed of to <hi>Richard Chiſwell</hi> and his Aſſigns If any Perſon Print any others (except thoſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the Author's Life-time) they are to be look'd upon as Spurious and Falſe: And the Publiſhers will be proceeded againſt according to Law.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
